{
  "reference_number": "10739",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "The target needs to be in law and not able to be weakened, only strengthened. Sucessive governements have pissed around and\n passed the buck on this issue for my entire lifetime. You need to stop that happening and make sure future governments, what ever\n\n their colour, have to act."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "We have to treat all emissions. We have to act based on the impact emissions have on our planet not on their source. The planet\n doesn't care about the source, only the impact."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "We should do domestic reductions as far as possible and always chose domestic over international but if we have to use international\n\n then make sure it legitimate."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Only revision allowed should be to do it sooner and faster."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "only to make reductions to happen faster."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree that the Government and the Climate Commission should take the following factors into consideration when advising on and\nsetting budgets: • scientific knowledge regarding climate change • technology relevant to climate change • economic\n\ncircumstances and the likely impact of a decision on the economy, as well as the competitiveness of particular sectors of the\neconomy • fiscal circumstances and the likely impact of the decision on taxation, public spending and public borrowing • social\ncircumstances and the likely impact of a decision on fuel poverty • energy policy and the likely impact of a decision on energy\n\nsupplies and the carbon and energy intensity of the economy."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes - we must learn from the mistakes of the UK's Climate Change Act and specify a strict time frame for producing a plan."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The Government’s policy plans to meet emission budgets should be comprehensive, fair, cost-effective, environmentally sustainable,\n\nand reflect a commitment to Te Tiriti o Waitangi. It must not be gender biased. It must not be baised on technology changes that may\nor may not happen."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes - the Commission should not be a decision-making body. However, the Government should be legally required to consider and\n\nformally respond to the Commission’s advice, and to provide an explanation if they do not act on it."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "The Commission should advise the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS. It should not make decisions itself with respect to\nthe number of units available in the NZ ETS, or its implementation."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree with the following collective expertise: • climate change policy (including emissions trading) • resource economics and\nimpacts (including social impacts, labour markets and distribution) • te Tiriti o Waitangi, te reo me ona tikanga Māori and Māori\n\ninterests • climate and environmental science including mātauranga Māori • experience with addressing adaptation challenges like\nplanning, insurance and local government • risk management • engineering and/or infrastructure • community engagement and\n\ncommunications. • business competitiveness • knowledge of the public and private innovation and technology development system.\nI think expertise in public health and resiliance is also important."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes. This may require a separate adaptation sub-committee within the Climate Commission."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree with the proposed functions below, but recognise that nuance is required in terms of how local councils are involved: • a\n\nnational climate change risk assessment • a national adaptation plan • regular review of progress towards implementing the national\nadaptation plan • an adaptation reporting power"
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Act for the children now."
    }
  ]
}
